Guide to the Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
- Series I. Correspondence to or from Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
  - 1786-1794
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Marie Anne Pierrette Lavoisier (Paulze), Port-Royal to Paris, December 19, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Letter begins: "tu te donne ma chere bonne / amie bien de la peine, bien de / la fatigue de corps et desprit…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Manuscripts, Fall 1958, v. 10, pg. 58-9.
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent], 29 germinal an II [18 April 1794], [to] the members of the Bureau de consultation des arts et métiers, April 18, 1794 (Box 43, Folder 17)
      Physical Description: 3 p. on 3 leaves. Copy of a letter.
      Summary: Lavoisier asks a certificate to account for his behavior since the beginning of the French Revolution.
      Letter begins: "Mes chers collègues/Le moment approche, du moins je l'espère, ou, rendu a des occupations dont il auroit été a souhaitter que je n'eusse jaMays été détourné..."
    - Dupin, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, January 10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Describes the benefits resulting from M. Baudon's position in the Ferme générale, to be distributed among his family and relatives.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / J'ai remis à M. Gondoin, Vôtre nottaire, les pieces nécessaires…"
    - Dupin, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, March 4 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Summary: Madame Baudon has chosen the lawyer Cottet to represent her in the disaccord between her and Lavoisier.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / il y a environ 15. jours que j'avois prévenu M. Gondouin…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] M. Cochereau, Paris, April 9 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 23 cm; manuscript Signed. Right margin of p. [1] torn with loss of text.
      Summary: M. Ledreau has been appointed in the tobacco section of the Ferme in Paris. "Monsieur / Vous avés bien voulu me faire connoitre L'intér[et] / que…"
      Letter begins: "me trouvant Monsieur et cher Parent deja tres chargé / de biens fonds…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur Parisis fils, Villers-Cotterêtes, Paris, May 18 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Turns down two business deals as a result of financial constraint.
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, July 19 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Thanks Lavoisier for the "ballot" she is to receive, and which she plans to give to the Carmelites.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur je prénderai Le ballot en / totalité…"
    - Dupin, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier?, December 19 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Summary: States that M. Baudon's mother has been authorized to be executor of his will and describes the functions she is to carry out.
      Letter begins: "J'ai l'honneur de vous prévenir Monsieur, que les / héritiers de M. Baudon…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] the Académie royale des sciences, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 21 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Draft of a letter describing Lavoisier's research on the composition of calcareous strata and asking for samples collected by Guettard and the Duc d'Orléans.
      Letter begins: "Les matieres qui se rencontrent des les pays / composés de couches calcaires…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur Le Goussat, Paris, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Summary: Asks his broker to have investments made for him.
      Letter begins: "Je crois Monsieur quesi les rescriptions / sont demain a 8 3/4 ou 9…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to an unnamed man], Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Unfinished letter expressing regret about the addressee's absence from Paris.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / Que votre absence est longue pour vos amis…"
- Series II. Correspondence to or from Marie-Anne Lavoisier
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to] M. Goudoin, February 15, 1782 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. holograph.
    Summary: Forwards, for her husband, an advertising poster of a house to be rented at Le Bourget.
    Letter begins: "M. Lavoisier a l'honneur de Souhaiter / le Bonjour a M. Goudoin…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, [to] Monsieur de Morveau, Dijon, October 9, 1787 (Box 43, Folder 20)
    Physical Description: 2 p. on 1 leaf; 18 cm; letter autograph signed
    Summary: Mme Lavoisier thanks Louis Bernard Guyton de Morveau for his welcoming her and her husband during their stay in Dijon.
    Letter begins: "Nous avons eu bien des regrets Monsieur d'être obligés de quitter Dijon si prontement..."
    Bibliographic Reference: Drouot 5 April 1974
  - Franklin, Benjamin [to] Madame Lavoisier, Philadelphia, October 23, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Physical Description: 3 leaves; 27 cm; holograph signed (photograph), original in the Archives nationales.
    Summary: Thanks her for the portrait she made of him, describes his good living conditions, and thanks M. Lavoisier for sending him the Nomenclature chimique.
    Letter begins: "I have a long time been disabled from / Writing to my dear Friend…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette,, [to Guyton de Morveau ], November 16, 1788 (Box 43, Folder 21)
    Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 21 cm; letter autograph
    Summary: Mme Lavoisier relates an explosion that happened during a chemical experiment about powder. Relates current events (the States Generals, eulogy of Buffon by Condorcet...)
    Letter begins: "Nous avons en effet Monsieur couru les plus grands dangers, à présent que mon ame est un peu remise du spectacle effroyable dont j'ai été témoin..."
  - Gillan, Hugh [to] Madame Lavoisier, London, May 4, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Physical Description: 4 leaves; 33 cm; holograph signed (photograph), original in the Archives nationales.
    Summary: Announces the upcoming visit of two gentlemen to Paris, who will deliver some oil paints ordered by Mme. Lavoisier.
    Letter begins: "Madam / When I solicited so earnestly the ho- / nour of permission to write to you…"
  - [to] Madame Lavoisier, Orléans to Paris, September 11, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Physical Description: 4 leaves; 24 cm; holograph (photograph), original in the Archives nationales.
    Summary: Describes the revolutionary turmoils, particularly in Orléans.
    Letter begins: "je n'ai point reçu par le courier du jour Mabonne / amie, les livres que vous m'annoncez…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to] les Citoyens administrateurs du Département de Paris, 1795 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Physical Description: 2 leaves; 27 cm; holograph signed.
    Summary: Requests a statement of her late husband's debts. Marginal notes in different hands, with signature and dates on p. [1].
    Letter begins: "La citoyenne Veuve Lavoisier / Aux citoyens administrateurs Du Département / De Paris / Demande à être autorisée à prendre…"
  - France. Commission des revenus nationaux, 1794-1795. (Rocher, Lammond [?], [and] Chardonvamiville [?]) [to] Madame Lavoisier, Paris, March 1795 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm; manuscript signed.
    Summary: The question of what she is to inherit from her father is under review.
    Letter begins: "Nous vous prévenons, Citoyenne, que / conformement à un arrêté du comité des / finances…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to a relative], September 1, 1795 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Summary: Refers to various financial matters and to some transactions with farmers from whom she expected payment in kind.
    Letter begins: "J'ai recu Mon cher parent les 38160 que / vous m'avez addressé…"
  - Ramel de Nogaret, Dominique Vincent [to] Madame Lavoisier, Paris, January 24, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm; manuscript signed. See also Lavoisier MSS. 2.42, 7.25, and 7.26.
    Summary: States that she may have her father's watch back if she can justify the legitimacy of her claim. Note in different hand, signed G. Noble (?) on p. [2], stating that the papers concerning the restitution of the watch are in order.
    Letter begins: "je vous préviens, Citoyenne, que je me Suis déterminé…"
  - France. Ministère de l'Intérieur, [letter] Paris, 5 thermidor an VI, [to] Cne Ve Lavoisier, July 23, 1798 (Box 43, Folder 22)
    Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 30 cm
    Summary: Tells Mme Lavoisier how to get a copy of the certificate of her release.
    Letter begins: "J'ai reçu votre pétition du 1er de ce mois par laquelle vous me demandés un duplicata de votre mise en liberté..."
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, 21 friMayre an X, [to] Citoyen Deterville, Paris, December 12, 1801 (Box 43, Folder 23)
    Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 15 cm; letter autograph signed
    Summary: Mme Lavoisier asks Deterville, a publisher, to publish Rumford's works.
    Letter begins: "Vous connoissez surement Monsieur la réputation de M. de Rumford, il fait imprimer ou va faire imprimer en Angleterre deux vol in-8° de ses ouvrages et mémoires..."
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, Crépy [-en-Valois], [to] Madame Gauthier, Paris, June 6, 1803 (Box 43, Folder 24)
    Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 19 cm; letter autograph signed
    Summary: Mme Lavoisier writes this letter to a friend, before travelling in Switzerland.
    Letter begins: "J'avais un très vif désir Madame d'aller vous porter mes remerciemens pour la lettre de recommandation que vous avez bien voulu me faire passer..."
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, an XII [1804], [to] M. Lenormand, Paris, 1804 (Box 43, Folder 25)
    Physical Description: 3 p. on 1 leaf; 15 cm; letter autograph signed
    Letter begins: "J'ignorais la mort de M. Dureville [?], Monsieur, je vous remercie de m'en avoir instruite..."
  - Morellet, André, [to] Madame de Rumford, ca. 1808 (Box 43, Folder 26)
    Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 13 cm; letter autograph signed
    Summary: Apologizes not to have visited Mme de Rumford because of the weather.
    Letter begins: "L'abbé Morellet envoye savoir des nouvelles de Madame de Rumford n'aiant pu en aller savoir hier à cause de la rigueur du tems qui l'empêchera de sortir aujourd'hui..."
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to an unnamed person], August 2, 1811 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Physical Description: 1 leaf; 16 cm; holograph signed.
    Summary: Apologizes for not being able to keep her business appointment and proposes another day.
    Letter begins: "Je vais diner alacampagne / mardi…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to an unnamed man], June 3, 1813 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Summary: Arranges to pay a debt she owes as heir of Mme. Sanchez (?).
    Letter begins: "jai leprojet Monsieur de Rembourser / les dix milles francs…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, [to] Monsieur Breguet, Paris, November 17, 1820 (Box 43, Folder 27)
    Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 18 cm; letter autograph signed
    Summary: Letter to Abraham Louis Breguet, a famous watchmaker, about a watch made for Mme Lavoisier.
    Letter begins: "Vous étiez l'autre jour Monsieur [si] occupé, si causant, si aimable, si caquet avec une très aimable dame que je n'ai pas osé vous distraire et déranger le moins du monde votre très actif tête-à-tête..."
    Bibliographic Reference: Librairie de l'Abbaye/4. 1968
  - Lavoisier, Marie-Anne-Pierrette, [letter autograph], [to] Monsieur Cuvier, Paris, March 3, 1825 (Box 43, Folder 29)
    Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 16 cm
    Summary: Invitation to a dinner
    Letter begins: "Mad. de Rumford espère que l'indisposition de Monsieur Cuvier n'aura pas eu de suite et qu'il voudra bien la dédomager lundi prochain en venant diner chez elle..."
  - La Fayette, Marie Joseph Paul Roch-Yves Gilbert du Motier, marquis de [to] Madame Lavoisier, Paris, February 2 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Physical Description: 1 leaf; 20 cm. Ms. signed
    Summary: On behalf of the Committee for Poland, he thanks her for her support and sympathies for Poland.
    Letter begins: "Madame / Le Comité que j'ai l'honneur de présider / en couragé par une heureuse experience de / vos genereux sentimens…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze) [to] the Département de la Seine, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Physical Description: 1 leaf; 20 cm. holograph signed.
    Summary: Refers to two statements from the communities at Le Bourget and Pierrefitte submitted in support of her claim that the trees on her properties in both areas rightly belong to her.
    Letter begins: "Citoyens / jevous ai fait passer aladatte du 26. pluviose / deux attestations..."
  - Dupont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel [to] Madame Lavoisier, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Physical Description: 1 leaf; 18 cm; holograph.
    Summary: Draft headed "Fin d'une lettre à Mme. Lavoisier" referring to debts he owes her and rectifying the accounts she has sent him.
    Letter begins: "Je vous vois du Zèle pour vous informer / en France de mes affaires…"
  - Lavoisier, Marie Anne Pierrette (Paulze)Letter, Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Physical Description: 1 leaf; 35 cm; holograph. See also Lavoisier MSS. 2.34, 7.25, and 7.26.
    Summary: Draft of a letter appealing to her legal rights for the restitution of her father's watch.
    Letter begins: "une lettre delacommision des revenus nationaux du 21 thermidor / an 3…"
- Series III. Correspondence to or from other Lavoisier's relatives or associates
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Aubert, Jean- François
    - Aubert, Jean- François, [letter about Louis Charles Waroquiez], Paris, [to] M. Durival, February 26, 1785 (Box 43, Folder 19)
      Physical Description: 4 p. on 1 leaf; 20 cm
      Summary: Accuses Louis Charles Waroquiez to have plagiarized him to write his Etat de la France.
      Letter begins: "Les renseignemens, Monsieur, que m'a donnés M. Le Noir, sur la personne et sur l'ouvrage de M. Waroquiez..."
  - Bailly, Jean Sylvain
    - Bailly, Jean Sylvain [to] l'Académie des sciences, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 10 x 21 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Forwards a memoir by a Mr. Bosset who wants to call himself "expert pour guerir plusieurs maladies," and asks for their evaluation.
      Letter begins: "j'ai l'honneur de vous envoyer, Messieurs, Le mémoir d'un Sr. Bosset…"
  - Berthelot, Marcellin Pierre Eugène
    - Berthelot, Marcellin Pierre Eugène [to] Monsieur le député, April 6, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 21 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Explains why the woods around Paris should be preserved in the interest of public health.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur le Député / J'avais trouvé chez moi la carte témoignant / dela visite que vous m'avez fait l'honneur…"
    - Berthelot, Marcellin Pierre Eugène [to an unnamed man], July 16, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 22 cm. Holograph signed.
      Summary: Inquires about the publication of Lavoisier's Œuvres and about the Lavoisier papers.
      Letter begins: "Cher Confrère & ami / Je prend la liberté devous écrire pour vous / demander confidentiellement…"
  - Berthollet, Claude Louis, comte
    - Berthollet, Claude Louis, comte [to] Dr. Blagden, Paris to London, March 9, 1785 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 31 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Reports on the experiments on the synthesis of water carried out by Lavoisier in February 1785 under Berthollet's supervision. He also mentions work done by Méchain, Haüy, Laplace, and Pingré. "Monsieur / L'on s'est beaucoup occupe ici ces derniers tems de la / belle découverte de mr Cavendish..."
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / L'on s'est beaucoup occupe ici ces derniers tems de la / belle découverte de mr Cavendish..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Annals of Science, 1954, v. 10, p. 59-62.
    - Berthollet, Claude Louis, comte [to] Madame Vimeux, Paris, May 9, 1811 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Announces that Mr. Ouitte has been nominated. Note in Madame Vimeux's hand on p. [1] expressing satisfaction that Berthollet took heed of her recommendation.
      Letter begins: "J'empresse, Madame, de vous apprendre / que mr Ouitte…"
    - Berthollet, Claude Louis, comte [to an unnamed man], Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 23 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Announces that Gay-Lussac, who had given in to Humboldt's entreaties to prolong his stay in Berlin, will return immediately upon Berthollet's advice.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et cher Confrére / Mr Gay Lussac cedant à l'amitié de mr Humboldt.."
  - Blagden, Sir Charles
    - Blagden, Sir Charles [to] Mr. de Luc, Pimlico, June 16, 1784 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Summary: Informs de Luc of the publication of a letter from Mr. Watt which will be printed in the Transactions of the Royal Society.
      Letter begins: "Dear Sir, / In answer to your queries. / 1. Mr. Watt has sent me the historical note…"
    - Blagden, Sir Charles [to] Berthollet, May 1817 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 19 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Draft of a letter forwarding the "cahier" of Thomson's Annals and discussing both Blagden and Biot's trip to France and the latter's trip to Edinburgh. Note in different hand on verso reading "Sr. Charles Blagden / Sr. Joseph Banks / Soho Square" "Le 1r de ce mois, mon cher ami, j'ai remis chez Mr / [...] franville le cahier des Annales de Thomson..."
    - Blagden, Sir Charles [to] Berthollet, June 13, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 23 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Draft in which he announces an issue of Thomson's journal, and mentions activities of Biot, Laplace, Berzelius and others.
      Letter begins: "Je vous avois […] mon cher ami, par la poste quelques jours avant / l'arrivée de…"
  - Brongniart, Alexandre
    - Brongniart, Alexandre [to] Monsieur Desnoyers, Paris, April 12, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm; holograph signed. Accompanied by envolope with seal.
      Summary: Regrets having not been able to give Desnoyers printed information about the history of the Bulletin des Sciences, and arranges for a future meeting.
      Letter begins: "Mon cher confrere, j'ai été hier a la Société / philomatique…"
  - Calonne, Charles Alexandre de
    - Calonne, Charles Alexandre de [to] M. de La Millière, June 5, 1786 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 20 cm; manuscript
      Summary: Draft of a letter forwarding the government's order for the nomination of commissioners to examine proposals regarding the rivers Yvette and Bièvre, and suggesting candidates. Corrections in Calonne's (?) hand.examiner les plans /"
      Letter begins: "J'ai l'honneur de vous envoyer, Monsieur, l'arrêt du Conseil / qui nomme des Commissaires pour "
  - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Les Martigues, September 13, 1810 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Summary: Describes the state of his sheep and property, and his experiments with steam boilers at Les Thernes.
      Letter begins: "j'ai eté enchanté, mon bon ami, / de trouber une de tes lettres à mon / retour de la campagne…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Les Martigues, November 10, 1810 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Summary: Describes ways of smuggling salt and his experiments with combustion and nitric gas at Les Thernes.
      Letter begins: "j'ai attendu vainement pendant 15 jours / une réponse a ma lettre de fontainebleau..."
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, May 21, 1812 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Summary: Discusses his contributions in relief of the job shortage in Amboise and his substitution of the sugar beet crops for Merinos breeding.
      Letter begins: "j'attendois detes nouvelles avec impatien/ce /, mon cher ami…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, May 25, 1813 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Summary: Gives an account of his experiments with distillation and fermentation.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, j'ai reçu ta Seconde / lettre dans laquelle je vois que…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup, May 29, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. Holograph.
      Summary: Incomplete letter discussing a shipment of white and brown sugar, problems with the crystallization of his sugar, the affair with La Nouvelle, and a purchase of coal.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, les beliers de mr / Weyer Sont partis ce matin…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, July 14, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Discusses the uneven coloring of his sugar loaves and the affair with La Nouvelle.
      Letter begins: "je m'etois bien appercu, mon cher ami, / que les pains de Sucre etoient plus colorés…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, July 18, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Summary: Discusses a business transaction concerning the mortgage on a house.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, mr petit m'a ecrit que le / duc de maillé vouloit payer…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, July 26, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Summary: Discusses the affair with La Nouvelle.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, j'ai différé de repondre ata / derniere lettre parceque j'esperois pouvoir te / donner des résultats…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, August 1, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Summary: Asks that the brown sugar he sent be returned to him because he can make more profit on it in Chanteloup than in Paris, and mentions his distillation difficulties.
      Letter begins: "j'apprends par mde dela tourette, mon cher / ami, que les pains de sucre…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Chanteloup to Paris, August 18, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Summary: Announces that the affair with La Nouvelle has ended and discusses the sums of money to be repaid.
      Letter begins: "enfin, mon cher ami, j'ai terminé avec la nouve/lle…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, October 3, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm. Holograph signed.
      Summary: Orders bone black and announces the shipment of six barrels of sugar to Paris.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, voyci le moment ou je / vais travailler mes betteraves…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, October 22, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Summary: Announces a messenger with liquor for M. Blondel and sugar for his son, and awaits his steam boiler and parts for hs graters on his messenger's return.
      Letter begins: "mon cher ami, thierry qui est parti hier mat/in / porte une piéce esprit…"
    - Chaptal de Chanteloup, Jean Antoine Claude, comte [to] Monsieur Chaptal fils, Paris, November 5, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 24)